<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
	<item>
		<content>
			<name>
				<![CDATA[CAREER & TECHNICAL EDUCATION]]>
			</name>
		</content>
		<item>
			<content>
				<name>
					<![CDATA[A. Foundational Academic Expectations]]>
				</name>
			</content>
		</item>
		<item>
			<content>
				<name>
					<![CDATA[B. Essential Knowledge and Skills]]>
				</name>
			</content>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS01 ACADEMIC FOUNDATIONS: Achieve additional academic knowledge and skills required to pursue the full range of career and postsecondary education opportunities within a career cluster.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS01.01 Complete required training, education, and certification to prepare for employment in a particular career field.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.01.01 Identify training, education and certification requirements for occupational choice.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.01.02 Participate in career-related training and/or degree programs.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.01.03 Pass certification tests to qualify for licensure and/or certification in chosen occupational area.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS01.02 Demonstrate language arts knowledge and skills required to pursue the full range of post-secondary education and career opportunities.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.01 Model behaviors that demonstrate active listening.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.02 Adapt language for audience, purpose, situation. (i.e. diction/structure, style).]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.03 Organize oral and written information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.04 Compose focused copy for a variety of written documents such as agendas, audio-visuals, bibliographies, drafts, forms/documents, notes, oral presentations, reports, and technical terminology.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.05 Edit copy to create focused written documents such as agendas, audio-visuals, bibliographies, drafts, forms/documents, notes, oral presentations, reports, and technical terminology.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.06 Comprehend key elements of oral and written information such as cause/effect, comparisons/contrasts, conclusions, context, purpose, charts/tables/graphs, evaluation/critiques, mood, persuasive text, sequence, summaries, and technical subject matter.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.07 Evaluate oral and written information for accuracy, adequacy/sufficiency, appropriateness, clarity, conclusions/solutions, fact/opinion, propaganda, relevancy, validity, and relationship of ideas.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.08 Identify assumptions, purpose, outcomes/solutions, and propaganda techniques.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.09 Predict potential outcomes and/or solutions based on oral and written information regarding trends.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.02.10 Present formal and informal speeches including discussion, information requests, interpretation, and persuasive arguments.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS01.03 Demonstrate mathematics knowledge and skills required to pursue the full range of post-secondary education and career opportunities.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.03.01 Identify whole numbers, decimals, and fractions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.03.02 Demonstrate knowledge of basic arithmetic operations such as addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.03.03 Demonstrate use of relational expressions such as equal to, not equal, greater than, less than, etc.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.03.04 Apply data and measurements to solve a problem.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.03.05 Analyze Mathematical problem statements for missing and/or irrelevant data.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.03.06 Construct charts/tables/graphs from functions and data.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.03.07 Analyze data when interpreting operational documents.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS01.04 Demonstrate science knowledge and skills required to pursue the full range of post-secondary and career education opportunities.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.04.01 Evaluate scientific constructs including conclusions, conflicting data, controls, data, inferences, limitations, questions, sources of errors, and variables.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS01.04.02 Apply scientific methods in qualitative and quantitative analysis, data gathering, direct and indirect observation, predictions, and problem identification.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS02 COMMUNICATIONS: Use oral and written communication skills in creating, expressing and interpreting information and ideas including technical terminology and information.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.01 Select and employ appropriate reading and communication strategies to learn and use technical concepts and vocabulary in practice.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.01.01 Determine the most appropriate reading strategy for identifying the overarching purpose of a text (i.e. skimming, reading for detail, reading for meaning or critical analysis).]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.01.02 Demonstrate use of content, technical concepts and vocabulary when analyzing information and following directions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.01.03 Select the reading strategy or strategies needed to fully comprehend the content within a written document (i.e., skimming, reading for detail, reading for meaning or critical analysis).]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.01.04 Interpret information, data, and observations to apply information learned from reading to actual practice.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.01.05 Transcribe information, data, and observations to apply information learned from reading to actual practice.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.01.06 Communicate information, data, and observations to apply information learned from reading to actual practice.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.02 Demonstrate use of the concepts, strategies, and systems for obtaining and conveying ideas and information to enhance communication in the workplace.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.02.01 Employ verbal skills when obtaining and conveying information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.02.02 Record information needed to present a report on a given topic or problem.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.02.03 Write internal and external business correspondence that conveys and/or obtains information effectively.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.02.04 Communicate with other employees to clarify workplace objectives.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.02.05 Communicate effectively with customers and employees to foster positive relationships.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.03 Locate, organize and reference written information from various sources to communicate with co-workers and clients/participants.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.03.01 Locate written information used to communicate with co-workers and customers.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.03.02 Organize information to use in written and oral communications.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.03.03 Reference the sources of information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.04 Evaluate and use information resources to accomplish specific occupational tasks.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.04.01 Use informational texts, Internet web sites, and/or technical materials to review and apply information sources for occupational tasks.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.04.02 Evaluate the reliability of information from informational texts, Internet Web sites, and/or technical materials and resources.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.05 Use correct grammar, punctuation and terminology to write and edit documents.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.05.01 Compose multi-paragraph documents clearly, succinctly, and accurately.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.05.02 Use descriptions of audience and purpose when preparing and editing written documents.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.05.03 Use correct grammar, spelling, punctuation, and capitalization when preparing written documents.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.06 Develop and deliver formal and informal presentations using appropriate media to engage and inform audiences.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.06.01 Prepare oral presentations to provide information for specific purposes and audiences.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.06.02 Identify support materials that will enhance an oral presentation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.06.03 Prepare support materials that will enhance an oral presentation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.06.04 Deliver an oral presentation that sustains listeners' attention and interest.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.06.05 Align presentation strategies to the intended audience.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.06.06 Implement multi-media strategies for presentations.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.07 Interpret verbal and nonverbal cues/behaviors to enhance communication with co-workers and clients/participants.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.07.01 Interpret verbal behaviors when communicating with clients and co-workers.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.07.02 Interpret nonverbal behaviors when communicating with clients and co-workers.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.08 Apply active listening skills to obtain and clarify information.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.08.01 Interpret a given verbal message/information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.08.02 Respond with restatement and clarification techniques to clarify information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.09 Develop and interpret tables, charts, and figures to support written and oral communications.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.09.01 Create tables, charts, and figures to support written and oral communications.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.09.02 Interpret tables, charts, and figures used to support written and oral communication.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.10 Listen to and speak with diverse individuals to enhance communication skills.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.10.01 Apply factors and strategies for communicating with a diverse workforce.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.10.02 Demonstrate ability to communicate and resolve conflicts within a diverse workforce.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS02.11 Exhibit public relations skills to increase internal and external customer/client satisfaction.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS02.11.01 Communicate effectively when developing positive customer/client relationships.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS03 PROBLEM-SOLVING AND CRITICAL THINKING: Solve problems using critical thinking skills (analyze, synthesize, and evaluate) independently and in teams. Solve problems using creativity and innovation.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS03.01 Employ critical thinking skills independently and in teams to solve problems and make decisions (e.g., analyze, synthesize and evaluate).]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.01 Identify common tasks that require employees to use problem-solving skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.02 Analyze elements of a problem to develop creative solutions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.03 Describe the value of using problem-solving and critical thinking skills to improve a situation or process.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.04 Create ideas, proposals, and solutions to problems.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.05 Evaluate ideas, proposals, and solutions to problems.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.06 Use structured problem-solving methods when developing proposals and solutions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.07 Generate new and creative ideas to solve problems by brainstorming possible solutions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.08 Critically analyze information to determine value to the problem-solving task.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.09 Guide individuals through the process of recognizing concerns and making informed decisions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.10 Identify alternatives using a variety of problem-solving and critical thinking skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.01.11 Evaluate alternatives using a variety of problem-solving and critical thinking skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS03.02 Employ critical thinking and interpersonal skills to resolve conflicts with staff and/or customers.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.02.01 Analyze situations and behaviors that affect conflict management.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.02.02 Determine best options/outcomes for conflict resolution using critical thinking skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.02.03 Identify with others’ feelings, needs, and concerns.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.02.04 Implement stress management techniques.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.02.05 Resolve conflicts with/for customers using conflict resolution skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.02.06 Implement conflict resolution skills to address staff issues/problems.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS03.03 Identify, write and monitor workplace performance goals to guide progress in assigned areas of responsibility and accountability.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.03.01 Write realistic performance goals, objectives and action plans.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.03.02 Monitor performance goals and adjust as necessary.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.03.03 Recognize goal achievement using appropriate rewards in the workplace.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.03.04 Communicate goal achievement with managers and co-workers.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS03.04 Conduct technical research to gather information necessary for decision-making.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.04.01 Align the information gathered to the needs of the audience.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.04.02 Gather technical information and data using a variety of resources.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.04.03 Analyze information and data for value to the research objectives.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS03.04.04 Evaluate information and data to determine value to research objectives.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS04 INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY APPLICATIONS: Use information technology tools specific to the career cluster to access, manage, integrate, and create information.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.01 Use Personal Information Management (PIM) applications to increase workplace efficiency.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.01.01 Manage personal schedules and contact information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.01.02 Create memos and notes.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.02 Employ technological tools to expedite workflow.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.02.01 Use information technology tools to manage and perform work responsibilities.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.03 Operate electronic mail applications to communicate within a workplace.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.03.01 Use email to share files and documents.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.03.02 Identify the functions and purpose of email systems.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.03.03 Use email to communicate within and across organizations.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.04 Operate Internet applications to perform workplace tasks.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.04.01 Access and navigate Internet (e.g., use a web browser).]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.04.02 Search for information and resources.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.04.03 Evaluate Internet resources for reliability and validity.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.05 Operate writing and publishing applications to prepare business communications.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.05.01 Prepare simple documents and other business communications.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.05.02 Prepare reports and other business communications by integrating graphics and other non-text elements.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.05.03 Prepare complex multi-media publications.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.06 Operate presentation applications to prepare presentations.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.06.01 Prepare presentations for training, sales and information sharing.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.06.02 Deliver presentations with supporting materials.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.07 Employ spreadsheet applications to organize and manipulate data.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.07.01 Create a spreadsheet.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.07.02 Perform calculations and analyses on data using a spreadsheet.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.08 Employ database applications to manage data.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.08.01 Manipulate data elements.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.08.02 Manage interrelated data elements.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.08.03 Analyze interrelated data elements.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.08.04 Generate reports showing interrelated data elements.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.09 Employ collaborative/groupware applications to facilitate group work.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.09.01 Facilitate group work through management of shared schedule and contact information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.09.02 Facilitate group work through management of shared files and online information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.09.03 Facilitate group work through instant messaging or virtual meetings.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.10 Employ computer operations applications to manage work tasks.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.10.01 Manage computer operations.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.10.02 Manage file storage.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.10.03 Compress or alter files.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS04.11 Use computer-based equipment (containing embedded computers or processors) to control devices.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.11.01 Operate computer-driven equipment and machines.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.11.02 Use installation and operation manuals.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.11.03 Troubleshoot computer-driven equipment and machines.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS04.11.04 Access support as needed to maintain operation of computer-driven equipment and machines.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS05 SYSTEMS: Understand roles within teams, work units, departments, organizations, inter-organizational systems, and the larger environment. Identify how key organizational systems affect organizational performance and the quality of products and services. Understand global context of industries and careers.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS05.01 Describe the nature and types of business organizations to build an understanding of the scope of organizations.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS05.01.01 List the types and functions of businesses.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS05.01.02 Describe the types and functions of businesses.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS05.01.03 Explain the functions and interactions of common departments within a business.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS05.02 Implement quality control systems and practices to ensure quality products and services.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS05.02.01 Describe quality control standards and practices common to the workplace.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS06 SAFETY, HEALTH AND ENVIRONMENTAL: Understand the importance of health, safety, and environmental management systems in organizations and their importance to organizational performance and regulatory compliance. Follow organizational policies and procedures and contribute to continuous improvement in performance and compliance.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS06.01 Implement personal and jobsite safety rules and regulations to maintain safe and healthful working conditions and environments.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.01 Assess workplace conditions with regard to safety and health.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.02 Align safety issues with appropriate safety standards to ensure a safe workplace/jobsite.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.03 Identify safety hazards common to workplaces.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.04 Identify safety precautions to maintain a safe worksite.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.05 Select appropriate personal protective equipment as needed for a safe workplace/jobsite.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.06 Inspect personal protective equipment commonly used for selected career pathway.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.07 Use personal protective equipment according to manufacturer rules and regulations.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.08 Employ a safety hierarchy and communication system within the workplace/jobsite.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.01.09 Implement safety precautions to maintain a safe worksite.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS06.02 Complete work tasks in accordance with employee rights and responsibilities and employers obligations to maintain workplace safety and health.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.02.01 Identify rules and laws designed to promote safety and health in the workplace.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.02.02 State the rationale of rules and laws designed to promote safety and health.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS06.03 Employ emergency procedures as necessary to provide aid in workplace accidents.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.03.01 Use knowledge of First Aid procedures as necessary.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.03.02 Use knowledge of CPR procedures as necessary.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.03.03 Use safety equipment as necessary.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS06.04 Employ knowledge of response techniques to create a disaster and/or emergency response plan.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.04.01 Complete an assessment of an emergency and/or disaster situation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS06.04.02 Create an emergency and/or disaster plan.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS07 LEADERSHIP AND TEAMWORK: Use leadership and teamwork skills in collaborating with others to accomplish organizational goals and objectives.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS07.01 Employ leadership skills to accomplish organizational goals and objectives.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.01 Analyze the various roles of leaders within organizations (e.g. contribute ideas; share in building an organization; act as role models to employees by adhering to company policies, procedures, and standards; promote the organization’s vision; and mentor others).]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.02 Exhibit traits such as empowerment, risk, communication, focusing on results, decision-making, problem solution, and investment in individuals when leading a group in solving a problem.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.03 Exhibit traits such as compassion, service, listening, coaching, developing others, team development, and understanding and appreciating others when acting as a manager of others in the workplace.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.04 Exhibit traits such as enthusiasm, creativity, conviction, mission, courage, concept, focus, principle-centered living, and change when interacting with others in general.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.05 Consider issues related to self, team, community, diversity, environment, and global awareness when leading others.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.06 Exhibit traits such as innovation, intuition, adaptation, life-long learning and coachability to develop leadership potential over time.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.07 Analyze leadership in relation to trust, positive attitude, integrity, and willingness to accept key responsibilities in a work situation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.08 Describe observations of outstanding leaders using effective management styles.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.01.09 Participate in civic and community leadership and teamwork opportunities to enhance skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS07.02 Employ organizational and staff development skills to foster positive working relationships and accomplish organizational goals.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.01 Implement organizational skills when facilitating others’ work efforts.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.02 Explain how to manage a staff that satisfies work demands while adhering to budget constraints.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.03 Describe how staff growth and development to increase productivity and employee satisfaction.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.04 Organize team involvement within a group environment.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.05 Work with others to develop and gain commitment to team goals.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.06 Distribute responsibility and work load fairly.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.07 Model leadership and teamwork qualities to aid in employee morale.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.08 Identify best practices for successful team functioning.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.02.09 Explain best practices for successful team functioning.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS07.03 Employ teamwork skills to achieve collective goals and use team members' talents effectively.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.01 Work with others to achieve objectives in a timely manner.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.02 Promote the full involvement and use of team member's individual talents and skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.03 Employ conflict-management skills to facilitate solutions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.04 Demonstrate teamwork skills through working cooperatively with co-workers, supervisory staff, and others, both in and out of the organization, to achieve particular tasks.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.05 Demonstrate teamwork processes that provide team building, consensus, continuous improvement, respect for the opinions of others, cooperation, adaptability, and conflict resolution.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.06 Develop plans to improve team performance.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.07 Demonstrate commitment to and a positive attitude toward team goals.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.08 Take responsibility for shared group and individual work tasks.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.09 Assist team members in completing their work.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.10 Adapt effectively to changes in projects and work activities.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.03.11 Negotiate effectively to arrive at decisions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS07.04 Establish and maintain effective working relationships with all levels of personnel and other departments in order to accomplish objectives and tasks.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.04.01 Build effective working relationships using interpersonal skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.04.02 Use positive interpersonal skills to work cooperatively with co-workers representing different cultures, genders and backgrounds.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.04.03 Manage personal skills to accomplish assignments.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.04.04 Treat people with respect.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.04.05 Provide constructive praise and criticism.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.04.06 Demonstrate sensitivity to and value for diversity.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.04.07 Manage stress and control emotions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS07.05 Conduct and participate in meetings to accomplish work tasks.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.01 Develop meeting goals, objectives and agenda.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.02 Assign responsibilities for preparing materials and leading discussions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.03 Prepare materials for leading discussion.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.04 Assemble and distribute meeting materials.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.05 Conduct meeting to achieve objectives within scheduled time.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.06 Demonstrate effective communication skills in meetings.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.07 Produce meeting minutes including decisions and next steps.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.05.08 Use parliamentary procedure, as needed, to conduct meetings.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS07.06 Employ mentoring skills to inspire and teach others.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.06.01 Use motivational techniques to enhance performance in others.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS07.06.02 Provide guidance to enhance performance in others.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS08 ETHICS AND LEGAL RESPONSIBILITIES: Know and understand the importance of professional ethics and legal responsibilities.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS08.01 Apply ethical reasoning to a variety of workplace situations in order to make ethical decisions.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.01.01 Evaluate alternative responses to workplace situations based on legal responsibilities and employer policies.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.01.02 Evaluate alternative responses to workplace situations based on personal or professional ethical responsibilities.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.01.03 Identify personal and long-term workplace consequences of unethical or illegal behaviors.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.01.04 Explain personal and long-term workplace consequences of unethical or illegal behaviors.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.01.05 Determine the most appropriate response to workplace situations based on legal and ethical considerations.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.01.06 Explain the most appropriate response to workplace situations based on legal and ethical considerations.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS08.02 Interpret and explain written organizational policies and procedures to help employees perform their jobs according to employer rules and expectations.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.02.01 Locate information on organizational policies in handbooks and manuals.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS08.02.02 Discuss how specific organizational policies and procedures influence a specific work situation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS09 EMPLOYABILITY AND CAREER DEVELOPMENT: Know and understand the importance of employability skills. Explore, plan, and effectively manage careers. Know and understand the importance of entrepreneurship skills.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.01 Identify and demonstrate positive work behaviors and personal qualities needed to be employable.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.01 Demonstrate self-discipline, self-worth, positive attitude, and integrity in a work situation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.02 Demonstrate flexibility and willingness to learn new knowledge and skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.03 Exhibit commitment to the organization.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.04 Identify how work varies with regard to site, from indoor confined spaces to outdoor areas, including aerial space and a variety of climatic and physical conditions.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.05 Apply communication strategies when adapting to a culturally diverse environment.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.06 Manage resources in relation to the position (i.e. budget, supplies, computer, etc).]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.07 Identify positive work-qualities typically desired in each of the career cluster's pathways.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.01.08 Manage work roles and responsibilities to balance them with other life roles and responsibilities.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.02 Develop a personal career plan to meet career goals and objectives.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.02.01 Develop career goals and objectives as part of a plan for future career direction.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.02.02 Develop strategies to reach career objectives.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.03 Demonstrate skills related to seeking and applying for employment to find and obtain a desired job.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.03.01 Use multiple resources to locate job opportunities.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.03.02 Prepare a résumé.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.03.03 Prepare a letter of application.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.03.04 Complete an employment application.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.03.05 Interview for employment.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.03.06 List the standards and qualifications that must be met in order to enter a given industry.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.03.07 Employ critical thinking and decision-making skills to exhibit qualifications to a potential employer.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.04 Maintain a career portfolio to document knowledge, skills and experience in a career field.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.04.01 Select educational and work history highlights to include in a career portfolio.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.04.02 Produce a record of work experiences, licenses, certifications and products.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.04.03 Organize electronic or physical portfolio for use in demonstrating knowledge, skills and experiences.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.05 Demonstrate skills in evaluating and comparing employment opportunities in order to accept employment positions that match career goals.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.05.01 Compare employment opportunities to individual needs and career plan objectives.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.05.02 Evaluate employment opportunities based upon individual needs and career plan objectives.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.05.03 Demonstrate appropriate methods for accepting or rejecting employment offers.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.06 Identify and exhibit traits for retaining employment to maintain employment once secured.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.06.01 Model behaviors that demonstrate reliability and dependability.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.06.02 Maintain appropriate dress and behavior for the job to contribute to a safe and effective workplace/jobsite.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.06.03 Complete required employment forms and documentation such as I-9 form, work visa, W-4 and licensures to meet employment requirements.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.06.04 Summarize key activities necessary to retain a job in the industry.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.06.05 Identify positive work behaviors and personal qualities necessary to retain employment.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.07 Identify and explore career opportunities in one or more career pathways to build an understanding of the opportunities available in the cluster.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.07.01 Locate and identify career opportunities that appeal to personal career goals.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.07.02 Match personal interest and aptitudes to selected careers.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.08 Recognize and act upon requirements for career advancement to plan for continuing education and training.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.08.01 Identify opportunities for career advancement.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.08.02 Pursue education and training opportunities to acquire skills necessary for career advancement.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.08.03 Examine the organization and structure of various segments of the industry to prepare for career advancement.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.08.04 Research local and regional labor (workforce) market and job growth information to project potential for advancement.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.08.05 Manage employment relations to make career advancements.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.09 Continue professional development to keep current on relevant trends and information within the industry.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.09.01 Use self assessment, organizational priorities, journals, Internet sites, professional associations, peers and other resources to develop goals that address training, education and self-improvement issues.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.09.02 Read trade magazines and journals, manufacturers’ catalogues, industry publications and Internet sites to keep current on industry trends.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.09.03 Participate in relevant conferences, workshops, mentoring activities and in-service training to stay current with recent changes in the field.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.10 Examine licensing, certification and credentialing requirements at the national, state and local levels to maintain compliance with industry requirements.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.10.01 Examine continuing education requirements related to licensing, certification, and credentialing requirements at the local, state and national levels for chosen occupation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.10.02 Examine the procedures and paperwork involved in maintaining and updating licensure, certification and credentials for chosen occupation.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.10.03 Align ongoing licensing, certification and credentialing requirements to career plans and goals.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS09.11 Examine employment opportunities in entrepreneurship to consider entrepreneurship as an option for career planning.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS09.11.01 Describe the opportunities for entrepreneurship in a given industry.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[ESS10 TECHNICAL SKILLS: Use of technical knowledge and skills required to pursue careers in all career cluster, including knowledge of design, operation, and maintenance of technological systems critical to the career cluster.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS10.01 Employ information management techniques and strategies in the workplace to assist in decision-making.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS10.01.01 Use information literacy skills when accessing, evaluating and disseminating information.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS10.01.02 Describe the nature and scope of information management.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS10.01.03 Maintain records to facilitate ongoing business operations.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[ESS10.02 Employ planning and time management skills and tools to enhance results and complete work tasks.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS10.02.01 Develop goals and objectives.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS10.02.02 Prioritize tasks to be completed.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS10.02.03 Develop timelines using time management knowledge and skills.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[ESS10.02.04 Use project-management skills to improve workflow and minimize costs.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
		</item>
		<item>
			<content>
				<name>
					<![CDATA[C. Cluster (Foundation) Knowledge and Skills]]>
				</name>
			</content>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[AGC AGRICULTURE, FOOD & NATURAL RESOURCES: The production, processing, marketing, distribution, financing, and development of agricutlural commodities and resources including food, fiber, wood products, natural resources, horticulture, and other plant and animal products/resources.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC01 ACADEMIC FOUNDATIONS: Achieve additional academic knowledge and skills required to pursue the full range of career and postsecondary education opportunities within a career cluster.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC02 COMMUNICATIONS: Use oral and written communication skills in creating, expressing and interpreting information and ideas including technical terminology and information.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC02.01 Use oral and written communication skills in creating, expressing and interpreting information and ideas including technical terminology to communicate technical information within AFNR.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC02.01.01 Write clearly to communicate written ideas, results and questions to all types of people.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC02.01.02 Model the use of strategies and techniques for enhancing the clarity and effectiveness of oral communication in order to engage in dialogue with members of an example career field.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC02.02 Employ the use of technical information effectively to maintain and communicate records and reporting procedures commonly used in the AFNR cluster.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC02.02.01 Document work and processes using technical communication methods and protocols.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC03 PROBLEM-SOLVING AND CRITICAL THINKING: Solve problems using critical thinking skills (analyze, synthesize, and evaluate) independently and in teams. Solve problems using creativity and innovation.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC03.01 Access and utilize suitable resources to identify and study public policies, issues and regulations impacting AFNR management.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC03.01.01 Review regulations and major laws to evaluate their impact on AFNR management.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC03.01.02 Read appropriate written material to stay abreast of current issues impacting AFNR management.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC03.01.03 Gather public input for AFNR management decision-making.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC03.01.04 Use critical thinking skills to identify, organize alternatives, and evaluate public policy issues related to AFNR.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC04 INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY APPLICATIONS: Use information technology tools specific to the career cluster to access, manage, integrate, and create information.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC04.01 Access, manage, integrate and create information using information technology tools specific to AFNR in order to facilitate people, machines, and logistics.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC04.01.01 Use Geographic Information System/Global Positioning System (GIS/GPS) applications.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC05 SYSTEMS: Understand roles within teams, work units, departments, organizations, inter-organizational systems, and the larger environment. Identify how key organizational systems affect organizational performance and the quality of products and services. Understand global context of industries and careers.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC05.01 Examine and summarize roles within teams, work units, departments, organizations, interorganizational systems, and the larger environment to understand the nature and scope of AFNR organizations and the AFNR industry.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC05.01.01 Examine company performance and goals within AFNR organizations and the AFNR industry.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC05.02 Identify how key organizational systems affect organizational performance and the quality of products and services to demonstrate an understanding of how AFNR systems are managed and improved.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC05.02.01 Manage and improve organizational systems to better serve customers.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC05.02.02 Summarize the components and maintenance requirements of each agricultural, natural resource, and environmental system.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC05.02.03 Research geographical data to recognize the types of systems used in various geographical areas.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC06 SAFETY, HEALTH AND ENVIRONMENTAL: Understand the importance of health, safety, and environmental management systems in organizations and their importance to organizational performance and regulatory compliance. Follow organizational policies and procedures and contribute to continuous improvement in performance and compliance.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC06.01 Maintain safe and healthful working conditions and environment that adhere to employee rights and responsibilities and employer obligations in order to promote well-being in the AFNR workplace.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.01.01 Assess workplace conditions with regard to safety and health.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.01.02 Demonstrate application of rules and laws designed to promote safety and health.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.01.03 Apply safety/health precautions to participation in natural resource projects.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.01.04 Demonstrate recognized first aid knowledge and procedures to show how they are used by natural resource industries.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.01.05 Identify health/safety policies and procedures for natural resource occupations.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC06.02 Assess and control types and sources of workplace hazards common to the AFNR industry in order to demonstrate a working understanding of key health and safety concerns.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.02.01 Demonstrate methods to correct common hazards.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.02.02 Demonstrate application of personal and group health and safety practices.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC06.03 Examine and summarize importance of health, safety, and environmental management systems in AFNR organizations to express their importance to organizational performance and regulatory compliance.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.03.01 Examine required regulations to maintain/improve safety, health and environmental management systems.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.03.02 Develop a plan to maintain and improve health, safety and environmental compliance and performance.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.03.03 State the importance of safety, health and environmental responsibilities in the workplace to provide operating guidelines.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.03.04 Examine health risks associated with a particular skill to better form personnel safety guidelines.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.03.05 Develop response plans to handle emergencies.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC06.03.06 Identify hazards and acquire first aid skills to promote environmental safety.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC07 LEADERSHIP AND TEAMWORK: Use leadership and teamwork skills in collaborating with others to accomplish organizational goals and objectives.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC08 ETHICS AND LEGAL RESPONSIBILITIES: Know and understand the importance of professional ethics and legal responsibilities.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC08.01 Demonstrate workplace ethics specific to AFNR occupations in order to reflect effective stewardship of resources.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC08.01.01 Demonstrate evidence of interest and concern for natural resource stewardship and ethics.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC08.01.02 Exercise personal habits and actions to demonstrate workplace ethics.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC09 EMPLOYABILITY AND CAREER DEVELOPMENT: Know and understand the importance of employability skills. Explore, plan, and effectively manage careers. Know and understand the importance of entrepreneurship skills.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC09.01 Explain written organizational policies, rules and procedures common the AFNR workplaces to ensure employees perform job functions effectively.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC09.01.01 Locate appropriate information on organizational policies in handbooks and manuals.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC09.01.02 Discuss how specific organizational policies and rules influence a specific work situation.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC09.02 Select, research and examine critical aspects of career opportunities in one or more AFNR career pathways in order to gain an understanding of the breadth of occupations within this cluster.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC09.02.01 Locate and identify career opportunities that appeal to personal career goals.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC09.02.02 Match personal interest and aptitudes to selected careers.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[AGC10 TECHNICAL SKILLS: Use the technical knowledge and skills required to pursue the targeted careers for all pathways in the career cluster, including knowledge of design, operation, and maintenance of technological systems critical to the career cluster.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC10.01]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.01.01 Use technological systems to accomplish objectives in transportation.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.01.02 Select and improve utilization of technological systems to improve production and products.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.01.03 Identify technical skills needed to run an industry efficiently.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.01.04 Establish criteria to identify areas that have special needs for technical skills.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC10.02 Use tools, equipment, machinery and technology to work in areas related to AFNR.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.02.01 Select the appropriate tool to perform a given task.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.02.02 Maintain the working order of natural resources and tools for efficient work use.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.02.03 Wear protective equipment and handle natural resource tools and equipment with skill to demonstrate safe use of tools and equipment.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.02.04 Use tools and technology devices to assist in expanding human capacity for natural resource tasks.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC10.03 Compare and contrast issues affecting the AFNR industry including biotechnology, employment, safety, environmental and animal welfare to demonstrate an understanding of the trends and issues important to careers in this industry.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.03.01 Select solutions for different environmental issues.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.03.02 Analyze solutions for different environmental issues.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.03.03 Present solutions for different environmental issues.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.03.04 Learn economic principles in order to apply them to natural resource systems (i.e., supply, demand and profit).]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGC10.04 Envision emerging technology and globalization and project its influence on widespread markets to demonstrate an understanding of technologies and trends that will impact the AFNR industry.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.04.01 Examine new technologies to project their impact in the global market of technology.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGC10.04.02 Discuss the relationship between the advancement of technology and the need for continuing education/ career development.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[D. PATHWAY KNOWLEDGE AND SKILLS: The Pathway Knowledge and Skills Chart describes what all/most learners/workers need to know and be able to do to demonstrate competence within a career pathway.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGPA01 FOOD PRODUCTS AND PROCESSING SYSTEMS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPA01.01 Design and implement procedures and plans that demonstrate application of food processing principles to manage quality control in the food product and processing industry.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.01.01 Develop management plans to maintain equipment and facilities.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.01.02 Interpret Hazard Analysis Critical Control Point (HACCP) procedures when establishing operating parameters.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.01.03 Develop Hazard Analysis Critical Control Point (HACCP) procedures when establishing operating parameters.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.01.04 Implement Hazard Analysis Critical Control Point (HACCP) procedures when establishing operating parameters.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPA01.02 Conduct food product development and research activities that demonstrate application of food science principles to enhance products.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.02.01 Execute key processes related to food product development and enhancement.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPA01.03 Plan, implement, manage, and/or provide services associated with the preservation and packaging of food and food products to prepare products for distribution.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.03.01 Prepare products for distribution using an analysis of available product preparation options.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.03.02 Develop food preservation programs using appropriate food preservation methods.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPA01.04 Identify and apply food processing, handling, and storage factors to demonstrate their impact on product quality and safety.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.04.01 Develop a “quality factors program” to comply with local, national, governmental, and international standards.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPA01.04.02 Develop slaughter/inspection techniques to process food products and analyze food product options.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGPB01 PLANT SYSTEMS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPB01.01 Produce and manage plants in both domesticated and natural environments using application of principles of anatomy and physiology to enhance plant production.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.01 Analyze nutritional requirements and environmental conditions.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.02 Evaluate nutritional requirements and environmental conditions.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.03 Develop a fertilization plan using the results of an analysis and evaluation of nutritional requirements and environmental conditions.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.04 Implement a fertilization plan using the results of an analysis and evaluation of nutritional requirements and environmental conditions.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.05 Evaluate soil/media nutrients using tests of appropriate materials and/or by examining data.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.06 Manage soil/media nutrients using tests of appropriate materials and/or by examining data.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.07 Explain basic methods for reproducing and propagating plants.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.08 Employ basic methods for reproducing and propagating plants.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.09 Develop a plan for integrated pest management.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.01.10 Implement a plan for integrated pest management.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPB01.02 Examine and explain basic plant anatomy and physiology using taxonomic and other classifications to build a working understanding of functional differences among plant structures.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.02.01 Examine unique plant properties to identify/describe functional differences in plant structures including roots, stems, flowers, leaves and fruit.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.02.02 Classify plants based on physiology for taxonomic or other classifications.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPB01.03 Examine and apply fundamentals of production and harvesting when producing plants to demonstrate plant management and production techniques.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.03.01 Develop a production plan that applies the fundamentals of plant management.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.03.02 Harvest crops using methods that apply fundamentals of plant management.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.03.03 Handle crops using methods that apply fundamentals of plant management.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.03.04 Store crops using methods that apply fundamentals of plant management.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPB01.04 Exercise elements of design common to professionals in plant systems to enhance an environment for a variety of purposes (e.g., floral, forest, landscape, farm).]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPB01.04.01 Create a design using plants that demonstrates an application of basic design elements and principles.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGPC01 ANIMAL SYSTEMS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPC01.01 Produce and/or manage animals in domesticated and/or natural environments using an application of knowledge regarding anatomy and physiology to enhance animal production.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.01.01 Explain basic functions of animal anatomy and physiology using classification systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.01.02 State how body structures interact and affect animal health.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.01.03 Analyze a subject animal to determine the nature of its health status.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPC01.02 Recognize and interpret animal behaviors and execute protocols for safe handling to facilitate safety for both animals and humans.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.02.01 Develop a safety plan for working with a specific animal.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPC01.03 Provide proper nutrition using accepted protocols and processes to maintain animal performance.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.03.01 Examine animal developmental stages.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.03.02 Explain why nutrient requirements are different throughout an animal's life cycle.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.03.03 Analyze feedstuffs and the animal nutrient requirement and determine if the ration is adequate.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.03.04 Assess whether the nutritional requirements of a given animal are being met by recording performance and comparing feed variations.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPC01.04 Analyze and summarize factors that influence an animal’s reproductive cycle to demonstrate an understanding of the species response.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.04.01 Analyze the reproductive cycle based upon differences between male and female reproductive systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.04.02 Compare and contrast differences in reproductive cycles from species to species.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.04.03 Evaluate the breeding soundness of an animal.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPC01.05 Evaluate environmental factors affecting animal performance and implement procedures for enhancing performance to demonstrate an effective application of principles to optimize performance.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.05.01 Recognize optimum performance for a given animal species.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.05.02 Create a program to develop an animal to its highest potential performance.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.05.03 Assess an animal to determine if it has reached its optimum performance level.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPC01.05.04 Develop efficient procedures to produce consistently high-quality animals, well-suited for their intended purpose.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGPD POWER, STRUCTURAL & TECHNICAL SYSTEMS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPD01 SCIENCE]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD01.01 Apply physical science principles to engineering applications with mechanical equipment, structures, biological systems, land treatment, power utilization, and technology to facilitate work in the power, structural and technical systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD01.01.01 Relate power generation to energy sources.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD01.01.02 Sort and classify lubricants based upon lubricant application.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPD02 POWER]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD02.01 Apply principles of operation and maintenance to mechanicalequipment, structures, biological systems, land treatment, power utilization, and technology to facilitate work within the power, structural and technical systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.01.01 Maintain machinery and equipment by performing scheduled service routines.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.01.02 Operate machinery and equipment while observing "rules-of-the-road."]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD02.02 Apply principles of service and repair to mechanical equipment, structures, biological systems, land treatment, power utilization, and technology in order to maintain working equipment used in power, structural and technical systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.02.01 Service and repair the components of internal combustion engines using procedures for troubleshooting and evaluating performance.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.02.02 Service and repair power transmission systems following manufacturer's guidelines.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.02.03 Service and repair hydraulic systems by evaluating performance using maintenance manuals.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.02.04 Service vehicle electrical systems by troubleshooting from schematics.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.02.05 Service vehicle heating and air conditioning systems using company diagrams and schematics.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.02.06 Service and repair steering, suspension, traction and vehicle performance systems by checking performance parameters.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD02.02.07 Execute the safe and proper use of construction/fabrication hand tools in the workplace.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPD03 STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD03.01 Construct technical sketches, drawings and plans using basic skills in blueprint design and development to facilitate design tasks in the power, structural, and technical systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD03.01.01 Use computer skills to develop simple sketches and plans.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD03.02 Read and relate structural plans to specifications and building codes to facilitate building construction.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD03.02.01 Develop a logical construction plan based upon an examination of blueprints adhering to local building codes.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD03.03 Examine structural requirements and estimate project costs in order to facilitate effective planning for power, structural and technical system projects.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD03.03.01 Develop a complete materials list and project cost estimate using bids and billing information.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD03.04 Plan, implement, manage, and provide design and construction support services to facilitate the development of agricultural machinery, equipment, buildings, structures and technical systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD03.04.01 Design machinery and equipment including vehicles, implements, building, and facilities (e.g., feeding, feed storage).]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD03.04.02 Construct buildings and facilities following architectural and mechanical plans.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPD04 TECHNICAL SYSTEMS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD04.01 Use a variety of technology available to accomplish fast, accurate production in the power, structural and technical systems workplace.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.01.01 Identify various types of hardware systems and their applications.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.01.02 Explain various types of hardware systems and their applications.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD04.02 Design and operate control systems that use available power sources to facilitate work within agricultural systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.02.01 Execute procedures and techniques for monitoring and controlling electrical systems using basic principles of electricity.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.02.02 Design control systems by referencing electrical drawings.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.02.03 Install control systems by referencing electrical drawings.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.02.04 Troubleshoot a control system by referencing an electrical drawing.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPD04.03 Examine and summarize applications of geospatial technology to demonstrate a broad knowledge of technologies influencing the industry.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.03.01 Employ appropriate techniques to demonstrate application of GIS/GPS systems principles.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.03.02 Produce maps that reflect surveying and mapping principles using computerized applications.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[AGPD04.03.03 Orchestrate the planning, design, development and implementation of a project that applies geospatial technology to solve a practical problem in an area of personal expertise.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGPE01 NATURAL RESOURCE SYSTEMS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPE01.01 Conduct system management activities in natural habitats to demonstrate recognition of the important relationship between natural resource preservation and human intervention.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.01.01 Identify resource management components to establish relationships in natural resource systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.01.02 Apply cartographic skills to natural resource activities.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.01.03 Obtain planning data by monitoring natural resource status.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.01.04 Execute various natural resource enhancement techniques using scientific knowledge from the study of environment and wildlife.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.01.05 Recognize weather and other natural hazards related to working in an outdoor environment.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.01.06 Demonstrate natural resources mitigation techniques while following applicable rules and laws.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPE01.02 Communicate about natural phenomena using effective public venues to heighten awareness regarding conservation and resource preservation.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.02.01 Communicate natural resource information to the general public.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.02.02 Personally interpret natural resource phenomena to natural resource users.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPE01.03 Apply scientific principles and processes when planning and conducting natural resource management activities to determine the need, feasibility and application of logical, reasoned solutions to natural resource system problems and issues.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.03.01 Examine natural resource topics using science concepts, processes, and research techniques.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.03.02 Examine biological and physical characteristics to identify and classify natural resources.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.03.03 Examine natural cycles and related phenomena to describe ecologic concepts and principles.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPE01.04 Communicate about natural resource production practices and processing procedures to heighten public awareness regarding the responsible and sustainable use of natural resources.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.04.01 Prepare presentations to describe how natural resource products are produced, harvested, processed and used.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPE01.05 Practice responsible control and management procedures and techniques to protect or maintain natural resources in a variety of settings.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.05.01 Employ techniques and equipment needed to prevent wildfire.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.05.02 Use wildfire suppression techniques to demonstrate abilities in firefighting and control.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.05.03 Recognize symptoms of animal and plant diseases.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.05.04 Employ appropriate techniques to prevent the spread of animal and plant diseases.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.05.05 Recognize insect types and available controls used to prevent insect infestation.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.05.06 Treat insect infestation using appropriate insecticides.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPE01.05.07 Manage public gatherings and gain entry into secure, closed or restricted areas using knowledge of law enforcement procedures.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGPF01 ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICE SYSTEMS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPF01.01 Evaluate the impact of and plan for environmental services using analytic procedures and instruments to apply scientific principles to environmental systems management activities.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.01.01 Monitor samples using a variety of instrumentation.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.01.02 Calibrate and service instruments according to manufacturer's specifications.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.01.03 Measure operations by applying statistics, charts and scattergrams.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.01.04 Monitor operations by applying statistics, charts and scattergrams.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPF01.02 Examine and interpret public policies and regulations impacting environmental services to determine their effect on facility operations.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.02.01 Identify the major laws impacting environmental services by consulting reliable resource or participating in a training.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPF01.03 Apply scientific principles to the study of environmental service systems in order to facilitate development of solutions to environmental issues, problems and applications.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.01 Recognize weather systems and weather patterns using meteorological principles and knowledge.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.02 Describe soil compositions and properties to demonstrate knowledge of soil science.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.03 Explain well design and groundwater supplies using knowledge of hydrology.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.04 Discuss properties, classifications, functions and principles for managing wetlands.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.05 Discuss properties, classifications, functions and principles for managing watersheds.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.06 Use chemical analysis to conduct tests.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.07 Perform common microbiology procedures to examine cell types and conduct tests.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.03.08 Apply sampling techniques and other assessments using procedures and principles from the study of microbiology.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPF01.04 Operate environmental service systems (e.g., pollution control, water treatment, wastewater treatment, solid waste management, and energy) to manage a facility environment.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.04.01 Use pollution control measures to maintain a safe facility environment.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.04.02 Manage safe disposal of all categories of waste by applying principles of solid waste management (landfill operations).]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.04.03 Apply drinking water treatment operation procedures and principles to assure safe water for a community.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.04.04 Manage wastewater treatment and disposal operations using principles for managing wastewater and complying with rules and regulations.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.04.05 Apply hazardous materials management principles to assure safe conditions and compliance with applicable regulations.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.04.06 Explain conventional and alternative energy sources.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPF01.05 Use surveying and drafting tools, equipment, machinery and technology to accomplish planning and tasks in environmental services.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.05.01 Create maps of land, facilities, and infrastructure using technological tools.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.05.02 Demonstrate use of survey and drafting equipment used in planning of tasks in environmental services.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.05.03 Identify common pumps, vehicles, and instruments used in planning tasks in environmental services.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.05.04 Demonstrate design principles related to hyrdraulic sytems and high flow technologies related to fluid movement.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPF01.05.05 Install and maintain pumps and associated delivery systems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[AGPG01 AGRIBUSINESS SYSTEMS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPG01.01 Employ leadership skills to accomplish goals and objectives in an AFNR business environment.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.01.01 Develop a mission statement to guide business activities effectively.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.01.02 Apply leadership skills to accomplish general business activities from production to public relations.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.01.03 Apply management skills to accomplish general business activities from production to public relations.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPG01.02 Practice good record keeping strategies and techniques to accomplish AFNR business objectives.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.02.01 Prepare all files as needed for effective record keeping practices.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.02.02 Maintain all files as needed for effective record keeping practices.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPG01.03 Manage budget, credit, and optimal application of AFNR business assets using generally accepted accounting principles to promote business financial well-being.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.03.01 Employ fundamental accounting principles in business bookkeeping and associated financial files.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPG01.04 Assess and manage inventory using AFNR industry concepts and inventory control practices to ensure adequate inventory for business demand.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.04.01 Monitor inventory levels to accomplish practical inventory control.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPG01.05 Appraise, select and employ technological resources to accomplish AFNR business objectives.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.05.01 Use technology and information technology strategies for business improvement.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[AGPG01.06 Use sales and marketing principles common to agribusiness systems to accomplish AFNR business objectives.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.06.01 Conduct market research.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.06.02 Develop a marketing plan.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.06.01 Implement a marketing plan.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[AGPG01.06.01 Merchandise products and services.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
			<item>
				<content>
					<name>
						<![CDATA[SCC SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY, ENGINEERING & MATHEMATICS: Planning, managing, and providing scientific research and professional and technical services (e.g., physical science, social science, engineering) including laboratory and testing services, and research and development services.]]>
					</name>
				</content>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC01 ACADEMIC FOUNDATIONS: Achieve additional academic knowledge and skills required to pursue the full range of career and postsecondary education opportunities within a career cluster.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC02 COMMUNICATIONS: Use oral and written communication skills in creating, expressing and interpreting information and ideas including technical terminology and information.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC02.01 Prepare STEM material in oral, written, or visual formats that provide information to an intended audience to fulfill specific communication need of an audience.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC02.01.01 Use effective methods to communicate concepts of STEM to a broadly represented audience.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC02.01.02 Effectively communicate STEM information to a select audience.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC02.01.03 Apply the ability to read, interpret, and analyze STEM materials discerning the information and concepts.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC02.02 Apply active listening skills to obtain or clarify information pertaining to plans, processes, projects, or designs.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC02.02.01 Interpret messages or information provided that clarifies issues, ideas, plans, projects, or processes.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC02.02.02 Respond and/or restate information that will clarify STEM techniques to be used and/or information to be applied to projects, plans, or processes.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC03 PROBLEM-SOLVING AND CRITICAL THINKING: Solve problems using critical thinking skills (analyze, synthesize, and evaluate) independently and in teams. Solve problems using creativity and innovation.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC03.01 Effectively develop and apply the skills inherent in systems engineering where requirements, configuration, integration, project management, quality assurance, and process applications are necessary.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC03.01.01 Apply the skills and abilities in requirements analysis and configuration control while working plans, processes, and projects as assigned.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC03.01.02 Use the skills required in project management to track and assess the progress of a plan, process, or project as assigned.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC03.01.03 Apply the skills in quality assurance as well as those in process management and development for appropriate applications of systems integration techniques to an assigned project.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC04 INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY APPLICATIONS: Use information technology tools specific to the career cluster to access, manage, integrate, and create information.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC04.01 Effectively use information technology to gather, store, and communicate data in appropriate formats.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC04.01.01 Use IT in support of gathering, storage, and transfer of data or results in appropriate formats to support assigned projects.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC04.01.02 Select and use assorted forms of IT to meet the requirements of a plan, process, project, report, issue, or problem.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC04.02 Evaluate and use skills relating to the differing technological tools used to manipulate, report, or operate with data acquisition.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC04.02.01 Use IT tools to manipulate data creating reports, plans, processes, or projects from data provided.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC04.02.02 Use modeling, simulation, or visual reproduction to effectively analyze, create, and/or communicate to others regarding plans, projects, problems, issues or processes.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC04.02.03 Apply a currently applicable computer programming language to a process, project, plan, or issue as assigned.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC04.02.04 Apply statistical tools that verify the reliability or validity of the data used or collected in the plan, project, process, or problem.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC04.02.05 Apply a technological, scientific, or mathematical concept (use of algorithms) when communicating with others on issues, plans. processes, problems, or concepts.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC05 SYSTEMS: Understand roles within teams, work units, departments, organizations, inter-organizational systems, and the larger environment. Identify how key organizational systems affect organizational performance and the quality of products and services. Understand global context of industries and careers.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC06 SAFETY, HEALTH AND ENVIRONMENTAL: Understand the importance of health, safety, and environmental management systems in organizations and their importance to organizational performance and regulatory compliance. Follow organizational policies and procedures and contribute to continuous improvement in performance and compliance.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC06.01 Apply safety practices in the environment where science, technology, engineering, and/or mathematical principles are appropriate to ensure a safe workplace.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC06.01.01 Apply appropriate safety and health practices when developing plans, projects, processes, or solving complex problems.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC06.01.02 Use appropriate safety techniques, equipment, and processes in planning and /or project applications.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC06.02 Develop an awareness of safety, health, and environmental hazards inherent in the STEM arenas when solving problems, developing plans, processes, or completing projects to be proactive in promoting safety.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC06.02.01 Identify existing or potential hazards to existing or assigned plans, projects, or processes where safety, health, or environment might be in play.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>	
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC07 LEADERSHIP AND TEAMWORK: Use leadership and teamwork skills in collaborating with others to accomplish organizational goals and objectives.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC08 ETHICS AND LEGAL RESPONSIBILITIES: Know and understand the importance of professional ethics and legal responsibilities.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC08.01 Develop the knowledge and abilities to comprehend ethical and legal standards as they apply to STEM where plans, processes, and projects will be dependent upon them.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC08.01.01 Demonstrate the skill of application to ethical and legal standards as they apply to the plans, processes, and projects as assigned in simulated environments.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC09 EMPLOYABILITY AND CAREER DEVELOPMENT: Know and understand the importance of employability skills. Explore, plan, and effectively manage careers. Know and understand the importance of entrepreneurship skills.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCC09.01 Develop the skills and abilities to research career pathways in STEM.]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCC09.01.01 Engage experiences in STEM where an individual can identify personal interests and expectations for career and personal development.]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[SCC10 TECHNICAL SKILLS: Use the technical knowledge and skills required to pursue the targeted careers for all pathways in the career cluster, including knowledge of design, operation, and maintenance of technological systems critical to the career cluster.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
				</item>
				<item>
					<content>
						<name>
							<![CDATA[D. PATHWAY KNOWLEDGE AND SKILLS: The Pathway Knowledge and Skills Chart describes what all/most learners/workers need to know and be able to do to demonstrate competence within a career pathway.]]>
						</name>
					</content>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCPA ENGINEERING AND TECHNOLOGY]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA01 ACADEMIC FOUNDATIONS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA01.01 Apply the concepts and processes using the guiding principles and standards of school mathematics to solve STEM problems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.01.01 Apply and create appropriate models, concepts, and processes for an assigned situation, and apply them in solving the problem.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.01.02 Explain the impact of assumptions, initial conditions, boundary conditions, and other constraints on problem solutions.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA01.02 Apply and use algebraic, geometric and trigonometric relationships, characteristics, and properties to solve problems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.02.01 Evaluate mathematical solutions for reasonableness.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.02.02 Apply appropriate data collection, statistical analysis methods, and the means of displaying data to make decisions.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.02.03 Apply the processes and concepts for science literacy relative to engineering and technology.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA01.03 Demonstrate the ability to select, apply, and convert systems of measurement to solve problems.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.03.01 Apply scalar and vector quantities as applied to physical systems, such as the relationship between position, velocity, and acceleration.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.03.02 Apply fundamental laws and principles relevant to engineering and technology.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA01.04 Demonstrate the ability to use Newton’s Laws of Motion to analyze static and dynamic systems with and without the presence of external forces.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.04.01 Use the laws of conservation of energy, charge, and momentum, to solve a variety of problems involving mechanical, fluid, chemical, biological, electrical, and thermal systems.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.04.02 Use the relationships between energy, work, and power to solve a variety of problems involving mechanical, fluid, electrical, and thermal systems.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.04.03 Use the principles of ray optics to describe reflection and refraction of light.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA01.05 Explain relevant physical properties of materials used in engineering and technology.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.05.01 Explain the relationships between amplitude, wavelength, frequency, period, and speed of a wave.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA01.06 Explain the relationships between scientific theory, scientific principles and laws, in technology, and engineering.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA01.06.01 Develop concepts and processes for the application of technology standards.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA02 COMMUNICATIONS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA03 PROBLEM-SOLVING AND CRITICAL THINKING]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA03.01 Use mathematics, science, and technology concepts and processes to solve problems in projects involving design and/or production (e.g. medical, agricultural, biotechnological, energy and power, information and communication, transportation, manufacturing, and construction).]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA03.01.01 Apply the core concepts of technology and recognize the relationships with STEM systems (e.g. systems, resources, criteria and constraints, optimization and trade-off, and controls).]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA03.01.02 Develop the active use of information technology applications.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA03.01.03 Use computer applications to solve problems by creating and using algorithms, and through simulation and modeling techniques.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA04 INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY APPLICATIONS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA04.01 Select and use different forms of communications technology including word processing, spreadsheets, database, presentation software, email to communicate, and use of the internet to search for and display information.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA04.01.01 Select and use information technology tools to collect, analyze, synthesize and display data to solve problems.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA04.01.02 Read and create basic computer aided engineering drawings.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA05 SYSTEMS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA06 SAFETY, HEALTH AND ENVIRONMENT]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA07 LEADERSHIP AND TEAMWORK]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA08 ETHICS AND LEGAL RESPONSIBILITIES]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA09 EMPLOYABILITY AND CAREER DEVELOPMENT]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA10 TECHNICAL SKILLS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA10.01 Apply concepts and processes for the application of technology to engineering.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.01.01 Use knowledge, techniques, skills, and modern tools necessary for engineering practice.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.01.02 Describe the elements of good engineering practice (e.g. understanding customer needs, planning requirements analysis, using appropriate engineering tools, prototyping, test, evaluation, and verification).]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.01.03 Demonstrate the ability to characterize a plan and identify the necessary engineering tools that will produce a technical solution when given a problem statement.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.01.04 Effectively use project management techniques (e.g. working in teams, appropriate time management practices, effective organizational skills, conduct analysis of cost, resources, and production capacity, and quality practices with continuous improvement).]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA10.02 Develop processes and concepts for the use of technology which model technical competence.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.02.01 Use and calibrate probes, sensors, measuring systems, and devices to collect data using traceable standards.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.02.02 Explain the impact of error in measurement, predict the effect of error propagation in calculations, and record data with the correct number of significant digits.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.02.03 Safely operate a variety of tools, machines, and equipment (e.g. milling machines, rapid prototyping machines, drill press, band saw, CNC machines, and hand tools).]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA10.02.04 Use, handle, and store tools and materials correctly, perform preventative maintenance, understanding the results of negligence and improper maintenance or improper calibration.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPA11 DESIGN]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA11.01 Know the elements of the processes and concepts for understanding the design process.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA11.01.01 Explain why and how the contributions of great innovators are important to society.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA11.01.02 Explain the elements and steps of the design process and tools or techniques that can be used for each step.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA11.01.03 Describe design constraints, criteria, and trade-offs in regard to variety of conditions (e.g. technology, cost, safety, society, the environment, time, human resources, manufacturability).]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPA11.02 Develop processes and concepts to apply the design process.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA11.02.01 Apply the design process, including understanding customer needs, interpreting and producing design constraints and criteria, planning and requirements analysis, brainstorming and idea generation, using appropriate modeling and prototyping, testing, verification, and implementation.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA11.02.02 Demonstrate the ability to evaluate a design or product and improve the design using testing, modeling, and research.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPA11.02.03 Demonstrate the ability to record and organize information and test data during design evaluation.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
					<item>
						<content>
							<name>
								<![CDATA[SCPB SCIENCE AND MATHEMATICS]]>
							</name>
						</content>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB01 ACADEMIC FOUNDATIONS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPB01.01 Develop an understanding of how science and mathematics function to provide results, answers, and algorithms for engineering activities to solve problems and issues in the real world.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.01.01 Apply science and mathematics concepts and principles to resolve plans, projects, processes, issues, or problems through methods of inquiry.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.01.02 Use the knowledge and skills of science and mathematics to communicate with others on inquiry or resolution of issues/problems in the global community.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.01.03 Use the skills and abilities in science and mathematics to access, share, and use data to develop plans, processes, projects, and solutions.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.01.04 Use the skills and abilities in science and mathematics to integrate solutions related to technical or engineering activities using the content and concepts related to the situations.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPB01.02 Apply science and mathematics to real world situations that include the development of plans, processes, and projects where the issue is the solution of a real world problem.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.01 Demonstrate the ability to apply the Scientific Method to projects as assigned.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.02 Demonstrate the ability to recognize cause and effect when faced with assigned projects or issues.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.03 Differentiate between science and pseudoscience where conjecture is defined rather than the laws of nature.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.04 Demonstrate the ability to draw a conclusion when confronted with data or observations that focus on the observed plans, processes, or projects at hand.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.05 Recognize measurable attributes in units, objects, systems, and processes in assigned activities.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.06 Develop the ability to analyze change as a result of data differences and changing environmental values.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.07 Demonstrate the ability to research a topic, collect data, analyze the data, and draw conclusions from the results.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.08 Organize data, the consequences of the problems or issues, and research the material placing it in manageable formats.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.09 Use qualitative and quantitative skills to conduct a simple scientific survey, using the data to draw a conclusion based on the analysis.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.10 Predict the outcomes based on data collected in a project or experiment.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.02.11 Defend one's position based on collected facts and data supporting plans, processes, and/or projects.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPB01.03 Develop the ability to assess the impact that science and mathematics has on society when used to develop projects, or products for their use.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.03.01 Evaluate the impact of science on society based on products and processes used in the real world.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.03.02 Evaluate the impact of mathematics on society based on products and processes used in the real world.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB01.03.03 Investigate and evaluate how science and mathematics influence the professions and occupations supported by the STEM cluster.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB02 COMMUNICATIONS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB02 COMMUNICATIONS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB03 PROBLEM-SOLVING AND CRITICAL THINKING]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPB03.01 Use scientific and mathematical problem-solving skills and abilities to develop solutions to assigned projects that reflect the real world and their impact on modern society.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB03.01.01 Demonstrate the skills and abilities that foster effective problems solving techniques and processes.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB03.01.02 Apply appropriate and functional scientific methodology to the analysis and solution of problems.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB03.01.03 Use analytical tools and techniques to accurately and consistently make observations, make and record measurements at appropriate levels of precision, and collect data or evidence in an organized way to solve problems, construct tests, and evaluate data.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPB03.02 Develop the abilities and critical thinking skills needed to review information, explain statistical analysis, translate, interpret, and summarize research and statistical data collected and analyzed as the result of an investigation.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB03.02.01 Demonstrate and use effective critical thinking and reasoning skills by making and testing conjectures, drawing logical conclusions, and justifying thinking.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB04 INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY APPLICATIONS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB05 SYSTEMS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB06 SAFETY, HEALTH AND ENVIRONMENT]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB07 LEADERSHIP AND TEAMWORK]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB08 ETHICS AND LEGAL RESPONSIBILITIES]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB09 EMPLOYABILITY AND CAREER DEVELOPMENT]]>
								</name>
							</content>
						</item>
						<item>
							<content>
								<name>
									<![CDATA[SCPB10 TECHNICAL SKILLS]]>
								</name>
							</content>
							<item>
								<content>
									<name>
										<![CDATA[SCPB10.01 Demonstrate the knowledge and application of technical skills needed in a chosen scientific and mathematical field.]]>
									</name>
								</content>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB10.01.01 Develop the skills and abilities to design, innovate, operate, and maintain technological systems and equipment.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB10.01.02 Abilities to collect information, change and/or modify materials, and conduct experiments, using appropriate techniques, tools, and formulas.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB10.01.03 Determine the appropriate use and application of technology.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
								<item>
									<content>
										<name>
											<![CDATA[SCPB10.01.04 Critically evaluate data based on observation and experimentation.]]>
										</name>
									</content>
								</item>
							</item>
						</item>
					</item>
				</item>
			</item>
		</item>
	</item>
</root>
